Betsy Thornton Papers 1980-2010
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Betsy Thornton Papers
1980-2010
MS 495
Thornton, Betsy
The collection consists of materials which document the literary career of contemporary mystery writer Betsy Thornton. The bulk of the material is comprised of drafts of manuscripts, published articles and poetry, as well as printed materials including news clippings, copies of book reviews, and correspondence. One CD-ROM containing an interview is included.
1.5 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://www.library.arizona.edu/speccoll
Restrictions
There are no restrictions on this collection.
Biographical Note
Betsy Thornton was born Mary Elizabeth Thornton in Wilmington, North Carolina, the oldest of four children, to Elizabeth Mary (Kelly) Thornton and Colonel Robert L. Thornton. She was educated in Europe and the US graduating from Ohio Wesleyan University with a degree in English.
Thornton lived in England, France, Greece, Italy, New York City, and Venice, Calif. before settling in Bisbee, Arizona. In Bisbee she worked various jobs including director of the Cochise Fine Arts, a non-profit arts organization, and as a crime victim advocate for the Cochise Attorney's office.
Thornton's first publication was a chapbook of poems, On Davis Road in 1984. She is a recipient of a Poetry Fellowship from the Arizona Commission on the Arts. She turned to writing mystery fiction in the 1980's and her first mystery novel, The Cowboy Rides Away was published in 1996. The book introduces readers to her main character, Chloe Newcombe, who works as a victim advocate in Cochise County, Arizona, the same position that Thornton worked at the Cochise Attorney's office for fifteen years.
Thornton has published seven mystery novels including: The Cowboy Rides Away (1996), High Lonesome Road (2001), Ghost Towns (2002), Dead for the Winter (2004), A Whole New Life (2006), A Song for You (2008), and Dream Queen (2010). Her book, A Song For You, was nominated for the Mary Higgins Clark award in 2008.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into two series.
Series I: Writings, 1980-2010
Subseries 1: Manuscripts, 1985-2010
Subseries 2: Articles and Poetry, 1980-1984, 2000
Series II: Printed and Audio Materials, 1985-2010
Scope and Content Note
Papers, 1980-2010. This collection is comprised of the papers of Betsy Thornton. Items include published and unpublished writings including, manuscripts, poetry in published anthology, news articles, Thornton's reviews of works by others, and book reviews of Thornton's works by others. Printed materials include book manuscripts, news and magazine clippings and correspondence. One 29-minute interview, circa 2004, by Steven Nestor for WHUS radio show, Poets of the Tabloid Murder, is included on CD-ROM
Access Terms
Thornton, Betsy--Archives
Newcombe, Chloe (Fictitious character)--Fiction
American fiction--20th century
Authors, American--20th century--Archives
American literature—Southwest, New
Women detectives--Arizona--Fictio.
Crime--Fiction
Arizona--Fiction
Cochise County, (Ariz.)--Fiction
Mystery fiction
Container List
- Series I: Writings, 1980-2010
  Arrangement is alphabetical by title. This series contains the published and unpublished writings of Betsy Thornton. The Writings Series is divided into two subseries: Manuscripts (1985-2010) contains drafts of monographs. Articles and Poetry (1980-1984, 2000) contains published articles and poetry written by Thornton.
  - Subseries 1: Manuscripts, 1985-2010
    - The Cowboy Rides Away draft (1 of 2) undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - The Cowboy Rides Away draft (2 of 2) undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The Cowboy Rides Away edited draft (1 of 2) undated (Folder 3)
    - The Cowboy Rides Away edited draft (2 of 2) undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Dead For the Winter edited draft (1 of 2) undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Dead For the Winter edited draft (2 of 2) undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Dream Queen edited draft (1 of 2) undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Dream Queen edited draft (2 of 2) undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Dream Queen edited draft with notes (1 of 2) undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Dream Queen edited draft with notes (2 of 2) undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Dream Queen edited draft with notes (1 of 2) undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Dream Queen edited draft with notes (2 of 2) undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - High Lonesome Road edited original(1 of 2) undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - High Lonesome Road edited original(2 of 2) undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - A Song For You edited draft undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - A Song For You edited draft undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - A Song For You edited draft with author notes (1 of 2) undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - A Song For You edited draft with author notes (2 of 2) undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - A Whole New Life edited draft with notes(1 of 2), undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - A Whole New Life edited draft with notes(2 of 2), undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Unpublished original [Immaculate Conceptions] edited draft (1 of 2) undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Unpublished original [Immaculate Conceptions] edited draft (2 of 2) undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Unpublished Immaculate Conceptions edited draft (1 of 2) undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Unpublished Immaculate Conceptions edited draft (2 of 2) undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Unpublished Immaculate Conceptions chapters 13 and 19 undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 2: Articles and Poetry, 1980-1984; 2000
    - Articles and Poetry, 1980-1984, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Series II: Printed and Audio Materials, 1985-2010
  Arrangement is chronological.
  - Correspondence 1985-1994, 2001-2010 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Publicity – Reviews 1996, 2001-2007 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Publicity – General 1996, 2001-2009, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)